Hello
안녕하세요
"PyCon Korea's 7-year History We're Also Newbies to an Online PyCon"
"파이콘 한국 역사 7년 온라인 파이콘은 저희도 처음이라"
I am Yeoneui Hong from the PyCon Korea Organizing Team and I'll be presenting today
발표를 진행할 파이콘 한국 준비위원회 홍연의입니다
PyCon first started in 2014
파이콘은 2014년에 처음 시작되었고
and this is the 7th year that it is being held
올해로 7년째 열리고 있습니다
This is a picture from 2014
이 사진은 2014년의 사진이고요
2018, which is when I joined the PyCon Korea Organizing Team
2018, 저는 이때부터 파이콘 한국 준비위원회에 참여했어요
And 2019
그리고 2019년
And the anticipated year of 2020
그리고 대망의 2020년입니다
Actually, we had an exciting first meeting in mid-February this year
사실 올해 2월 중순에 새로 합류하신 파이콘 한국 준비위워회 분들과
with our new members of the PyCon Korea Organizing Team
설레는 첫 만남을 가졌는데요
It was mid-February, and we were really worried about gathering at the time
이때는 2월 중순이었는데 이 만남을 가질 때도 걱정이 많이 되어서
so for those who wanted to participate virtually
온라인으로 참여를 원하는 분들을 위해서
we provided a separate video conference link
별도의 화상 회의 링크를 준비하기도 했었어요
However
그런데
we later ran into an unprecedented situation
이후에 전례 없는 상황이 발생해서
and the 2020 PyCon Korea Organizing Team never gathered as a whole
2020 파이콘 한국 준비위원회가 다같이 모이는 일은 없었습니다
I think we did maybe once
한 번 정도 있었던 거 같아요
We had to meet virtually online
저희는 온라인으로만 만나야 했던 상황이었고
and since we had to change how we will hold the event, we began to discuss it
행사 방식의 변경이 필요해서 논의를 시작하게 되었습니다
I will share with you what discussions we had in order to
파이콘 한국 2020이 온라인으로 변경되기까지
turn PyCon Korea 2020 into an online event
어떤 논의를 거쳤는지 한번 공유드려 보겠습니다
To help you better understand, I will explain to you on how
이해를 돕기 위해서 2020 파이콘 한국 준비위원회가
the 2020 PyCon Korea Organizing Team works
어떤 방식으로 일하는지 설명을 드리려고 해요
First of all, we don't have a representative
일단 저희는 대표가 없습니다
Since we don't have someone representing us
대표하는 사람이 없고요
we did everything by discussing and making agreements
그렇기 때문에 모든 일을 대화와 합의를 통해서 진행하고
We had a lot of discussions
또 많은 대화를 나누게 됩니다
Nothing happens based on a single person's authority
누군가의 독단으로 일이 진행되는 경우는 없고
We all make an agreement to do something and share the responsibility
모두 합의를 통해 진행하고 책임은 나눠 지고
Instead, since everyone has different experiences
대신 각자 다른 경험을 갖고 있기 때문에
we discuss based on those experiences
그 경험을 바탕으로 해서 이야기를 나누고
and we also work together with the thought that we are all equal
또 우리는 모두 동등하다는 생각으로 일을 진행하고 있어요
However, I bet some of you are watching this and wondering
근데 이 내용을 보시면서 생각하는 분들이 계실 텐데
how we can work and make decisions by having so many discussions
이렇게 대화를 많이 하면 도대체 어떻게 일을 결정해서 진행할 수 있느냐
You could think that way
이런 생각을 하실 수도 있을 것 같은데
In order to make up for this
저희는 이런 부분을 보완하기 위해서
we have introduced and are using a tool called the 'gradients of agreement scale'
'의사 결정을 위한 동의단계자'라는 도구를 도입, 사용하고 있어요
I will briefly explain what this is
이게 뭔지 간단하게 말씀드릴게요
This is what it is
바로 이 내용인데요
If you take a look, this is how we can be a little more efficient
보시면 저희가 더 효율적이면서도
while listening to a little bit of what everyone has to say
모두의 이야기를 조금씩 다 들을 수 있는 방법이에요
You choose from the gradients of agreement scale that ranges from one to eight
1부터 8까지 나뉜 동의 수준 중 하나를 골라서
and before we start our discussion
저희가 논의를 시작하기 전에
we vote on a gradient of agreement that ranges from one to eight
1부터 8까지의 동의 수준 중 하나에 투표하고 논의를 시작합니다
If you look, there's whole-hearted endorsement
보시면 아주 적극적인 동의도 있고
and eight is 'veto'
8번은 '나는 안건을 거부한다'
which is where you reject a proposal so much that you'd block it
'안건을 저지할 정도로 거부한다'는 단계인데요
Since we voted in the very beginning
그러면 맨 처음에 투표를 진행했으니까
we discuss after the voting
투표를 한 후에 논의를 하고
and then vote again after the discussion
그 논의를 진행한 후에 다시 투표를 합니다
This is how we mediate opinions
그렇게 의견의 조율을 이뤄가는 것이죠
On March 11, we had our first discussion
저희가 3월 11일에 코로나 상황에 대응하기 위한
on how to respond to the COVID-19 pandemic
첫 논의를 진행했습니다
Honestly, at the time, we were all so confused
사실 저때만 해도 굉장히 혼란스러웠기 때문에
that we didn't even know what we should discuss about
어떤 논의를 해야하는지조차 알 수 없었어요
So we had a meeting on March 11
그래서 어떤 걸 논의해야 하는지
to decide on what we should discuss about
그것을 정하는 회의를 3월 11일에 진행했습니다
Here on the screen is an excerpt from our minutes from March 11
지금 보이는 화면은 3월 11일의 회의록을 발췌한 내용입니다
Since we had previously put together what to discuss about
3월 15일에는 앞에서 어떤 논의를 해야하는지 정리했기 때문에
on March 15, we discussed what options we had to choose from
결정을 위해 어떤 선택지가 있는지 논의했습니다
As you can see from the flow chart, "Should the PyCon be held or not?"
플로우 차트를 보시면 아시겠지만 "파이콘을 할까요, 말까요?"
"Should the event be held offline or virtually?"
"오프라인으로 진행할까요, 온라인으로 진행할까요?"
"Should the event still be held in August or not?"
"8월 개최를 유지할까요, 말까요?"
Since we have always held the event at COEX
심지어는 저희는 그동안 행사를 코엑스에서 진행해왔기 때문에
"Should the event be held at COEX or not?"
"코엑스에서 할까요, 말까요?"
We came up with these options
이런 선택지들이 생겨났었습니다
So on March 18, based on the choices we had drawn
그렇게 3월 18일에는 도출된 선택지들을 바탕으로
we discussed using the gradient of agreement scale
아까 앞에서 말씀드렸던 동의단계자를 활용해서 논의를 진행했어요
As you can see, this is an extract from our minutes from March 18
보시면 아시겠지만 이게 3월 18일 회의록 내용을 발췌한 건데
Whole-hearted endorsement, agreement with a minor point of contention
적극적 동의, 동의하고 사소한 논점은 있음
We've covered them up right now, but we wrote down every opinion here
여기에 원래는 의견이 다 적혀 있던 거거든요 지금은 마스킹을 해뒀지만
We even had people who vetoed
심지어 굉장히 거부하는 분들의 의견도 있었고
and everyone's opinions varied
의견이 다양하게 분포되어 있었습니다
Because everyone's opinions were so diverse, we couldn't come to a conclusion
이렇게까지 의견이 각양각색이었기 때문에 도무지 결론이 나지 않았었는데요
Since we had each expressed our initial level of agreement on March 18
3월 18일에 자신의 1차 동의 수준을 어느 정도 표현했기 때문에
and also held a discussion
그리고 또 토론을 진행했으니까
we conducted a preliminary survey the following week
그 후 일주일 동안 앞서 말씀드렸던 동의단계자를 통해서 사전 설문조사를 진행했어요
This is the survey that we conducted internally
이게 내부에서 진행했던 설문조사 폼입니다
And a week later on March 25
그리고 일주일이 지난 3월 25일에
we held a meeting with the tremendous title 'The Concluding Meeting and Vote Regarding
무려 '파이콘 한국 2020 개최 투표 및 코로나19 대책 종결 회의'라는
Holding PyCon Korea 2020 and Measures for COVID-19'
어마어마한 이름의 회의에서
We held a discussion based on the preliminary survey results
사전 설문조사 결과를 바탕으로 다시 논의를 진행했어요
On March 25, through a virtual meeting
그리고 3월 25일 온라인 회의 현장에서 최종으로
we held a final vote on our level of agreement
자신의 동의 수준을 마지막으로 투표했습니다
And finally
그리고 마침내
we landed on this conclusion
이런 결론을 내리게 됩니다
As you previously saw on the flow chart, Choice 1 was
선택 1은 아까 플로우차트 보셨겠지만
Should the PyCon be held?
파이콘을 할까요?
Yes, the event will be held in whatever format
네, 어떠한 형태로든 행사를 진행은 합니다
Second, should the event be held offline?
두 번째는 오프라인으로 진행할까요?
No, let's hold it virtually
아니요, 이건 온라인으로 진행합시다
Should we still hold it in August?
8월을 유지할까요?
Actually, just discussing about Choices 1 and 2 took up a lot of time
이건 사실 선택 1, 2만 얘기하는 데에도 진짜 많은 시간이 걸렸어요
so we couldn't finish talking about Choice 3 during this meeting
그래서 선택 3은 이날 회의에서 끝내지도 못했습니다
Although the conclusion was somewhat made
결론이 어느 정도 났으니 끝났다고 생각했지만
we still had to decide on the date of the event
개최 기간을 최종으로 확정해야 했어요
We held this meeting on April 1
이 회의는 4월 1일에 진행했고요
As you can see, there were various opinions to hold it in mid-September,
보시면 9월 중순에 하자, 9월 마지막 주에 하자
on the last week of September, that October was too late
10월은 너무 늦은 것 같다 이런 여러 의견들이 있었고
Finally, on April 3, many of you probably saw this
마침내 4월 3일에, 아마 많은 분들이 보셨겠죠?
We announced on PyCon's social media that the event will be held online
파이콘 SNS에 행사가 온라인으로 변경되었다는 공지를 띄우게 됩니다
As you can see from our process of discussion
지금까지 저희의 논의 과정을 보셨다시피
we went through numerous discussions to announce these four sentences to you
여러분께 이 네 문장을 전하기 위해 아주 많은 논의를 거쳤습니다
It definitely wasn't an easy process
정말 쉽지 않은 과정이었어요
Even afterward, our PyCon Korea Organizing Team
이후에도 저희 파이콘 한국 준비위원회는
continuously held discussions to decide how to hold a virtual PyCon
온라인으로 개최할 파이콘의 형태를 정하기 위해서 계속 논의를 진행했어요
how many days and hours it will be held
며칠 동안 진행할지, 몇 시간 동안 할지
how the sessions will be streamed
세션을 어떤 방식으로 송출할지
whether the event should be free or not and so forth
행사를 무료로 할지 유료로 할지 이런 것들을
and based on this, we decided one by one how the event would be held
이것들을 바탕으로 행사의 형태를 하나하나 만들어 갔습니다
The good thing was that we weren't the only ones preparing a virtual event
이때 좋았던 점은 이 와중에 저희만 온라인으로 준비하는 건 아니었거든요
We connected with PyCon organizers overseas who were preparing their events virtually
온라인으로 준비하는 해외 파이콘 오거나이저들과의 교류도 있었습니다
We shared documents regarding switching to a virtual event
온라인으로 변경된 상황에 대해서 서로 만든 문서를 공유한다든가
and held meetings with the members of PyCon APAC
파이콘 APAC의 멤버들과 회의를 한다든가
We were able to have such experiences
이런 경험도 가질 수 있었습니다
Some people commented that we were able to connect with PyCon organizers overseas
어떤 분은 오히려 예전보다 해외 파이콘 오거나이저들이랑
even more than before
더 많은 교류를 하게 된 것 같다고 말씀해주시기도 했어요
But everything didn't go so smoothly
하지만 모든 게 순조롭지는 않았습니다
As a preparation for our event
저희는 행사를 준비하기 위해서
we sign a provisional contract for the COEX Grand Ballroom a year in advance
코엑스 그랜드볼룸을 한 해 전에 미리 가계약 해두거든요
However, we couldn't help but cancel the provisional contract
근데 2019년부터 미리 잡아두었던 코엑스 그랜드볼룸 가계약을
that we had signed back in 2019
어쩔 수 없이 취소하게 됩니다
because the event was going to be held virtually
왜냐면 행사가 온라인으로 바뀌었으니까요
Since we were preparing for our first ever virtual PyCon, we were always talking
온라인으로 처음 파이콘을 준비하다 보니 논의도 계속되고 그랬는데
but even up to that point, the sense of closeness was relatively weaker
그때만 해도 오프라인에서 만나서 함께 하는 것 같은 친밀감은
than when we worked together in person offline
아무래도 상대적으로 부족하게 느껴졌었어요
Personally, after making the announcement on April 3
저 개인적으로는 4월 3일 공지가 올라간 이후
I went through what seemed like the Dark Age of our preparation from April to June
4월~6월에 행사 준비의 암흑기 같은 시기를 겪기도 했는데요
Finally, June came
그리고 드디어 6월이 됐고
and our preparation went into full swing
본격적으로 다시 준비를 시작하게 됩니다
If you are following our PyCon Facebook account, you probably saw this photo
저희 파이콘 페이스북을 팔로우하신 분들이라면 이 사진을 아마 보셨을 텐데요
It had been a while since the PyCon Korea had all gathered virtually
파이콘 한국 준비위원회가 되게 오랜만에 온라인에서 다같이 모여서
so we set up a Zoom virtual background that said 'We are Pythonistas'
'We are Pythinistas'라고 줌 가상 배경까지 설정하고
and took a group photo after the meeting
단체 사진을 회의 끝나고 찍었습니다
This is the PyCon Korea PyCon Korea Organizing Team's shared calendar
지금 보시는 건 파이콘 준비위원회 공용 캘린더인데요
The meetings were spread out in July
7월은 조금 뜨문뜨문 한데
but it was packed in August
8월은 어마어마하죠?
Honestly, August simply zipped by
8월은 어떻게 지나갔는지 사실 잘 모르겠어요
And now, it's September is ongoing
그리고 9월은 현재 진행형인데요
That's because this video was recorded
왜냐면 이 영상은 여러분이 보시는 행사 전에
before the event at which you are watching this
사전 녹화한 영상이기 때문입니다
Now, I'd like to share with you about what has changed
이제부터는 파이콘 한국 2020이 온라인으로 변경되면서
ever since PyCon Korea 2020 became virtual
무엇이 달라졌는지 공유해보고자 합니다
One of the goals we had while preparing for the PyCon Korea 2020
온라인 파이콘 한국 2020을 준비하면서 세웠던 우리의 목표 중 하나는
was to share our experience of having been together even in 2020
우리가 2020년에도 함께 있었다는 경험을
to those virtually participating in the PyCon Korea
온라인 파이콘에 참여하는 여러분에게 전달하는 것이었습니다
In order to do that, we prepared this session
그러기 위해서 저희가 이 행사를 준비하면서
so that we can share with you what kind of things we considered
어떤 고민을 하고 어떤 일을 했는지 공유하려고
and what kind of work we did
이 세션을 준비한 것도 있고요
Other than PyCon, there are probably many other communities
또 파이콘 이외에 다른 커뮤니티에서도
that are preparing to hold their events virtually
온라인으로 행사를 준비하시는 분들이 많이 계실 거예요
We hope we can be helpful to them as well
그런 분들께도 도움이 되기를 바라고 있습니다
First is the registration process
가장 먼저 등록 과정입니다
With PyCon's tradition of 'Everybody Pays'
파이콘은 'Everybody Pays'라는 기조를 가지고
participants, presenters, and even the PyCon Korea Organizing Team members
참가자, 발표자, 심지어는 행사를 준비하는 파이콘 한국 준비위원회까지도
all purchased tickets
모두 티켓을 샀었어요
However, our event was free of charge this time so there was no need to get tickets
근데 이번에는 행사를 무료로 변경하면서 티켓을 딱히 구매할 필요는 없었죠
since we were going to stream the event via YouTube Live
심지어 저희가 유튜브 라이브로 송출하니까요
Still, we created a process for ticket purchase just the same as before
근데 그럼에도 불구하고 지금까지와 동일하게 티켓 구매 과정을 만들어 두었습니다
We did it because we wanted to invite our participants to a virtual space
그 이유는 참가자 분들을 온라인 공간에 초대하기 위한 이유도 있었지만
but the biggest reason was that we wanted to give you the feeling
가장 큰 이유는 "내가 올해도 파이콘에 등록을 했구나"
of having registered to this year's PyCon
이런 경험을 여러분께 드리고 싶었어요
So to all participants who registered for this year's PyCon Korea regardless
그래서 올해도 어김없이 파이콘 한국에 등록해주시고 참여해주신 참가자 여러분
thank you very much
정말 감사합니다
Second is changes regarding the sessions
두 번째는 세션과 관련된 변경인데요
Up until now, all presentations were held at the COEX Grand Ballroom
지금까지는 코엑스 그랜드볼룸에서 모든 발표가 진행되었는데
At PyCon Korea 2020, we have recorded all presentations in advance
이번 파이콘 한국 2020은 모든 발표를 사전 녹화해서
and streaming it on YouTube like you are watching right now
지금 보시는 유튜브로 송출하고 있습니다
If the presentations were streamed online in real-time
아무래도 실시간 라이브 발표를 하게 되면
there could be issues such as poor connection or quality
끊김이나 퀄리티가 낮아지는 이슈가 생길 수 있기 때문에
so we avoided that and also captioned the videos in advance so that everyone
그것을 막고 자막도 미리 달아서 청력이나 시청하는 환경에 관계 없이
could participate in this event regardless of their hearing or watching environment
함께 이 행사에 참여할 수 있도록 하고
The Keynote sessions in English were translated in advance
영어 세션인 키노트세션은 미리 번역해서 언어 장벽을 낮추고자 했고요
We even recorded the opening and closing videos in advance
심지어 오프닝 영상과 클로징 영상까지 사전 녹화를 하게 돼서
which personally made my heart ache a bit
개인적으로는 조금은 마음이 아팠어요
since there's something special about opening and closing an event
왜냐면 행사를 시작하고 끝맺음 하는 맛이 있거든요
but that couldn't be helped
근데 어쩔 수 없었죠
Anyway, recording 40 videos total that were each 25~40 minutes long
어쨌든 25~45분 정도 되는 길이의 영상 총 40개를
and checking them wasn't an easy process at all
모두 녹화하고 검수하는 과정은 정말 쉽지 않았습니다
We recorded the presentations
저희가 발표자 분들과 발표 영상 녹화를 진행한 게
from mid-August to end of August
8월 중순부터 8월 말까지였는데요
At first, the presenters had the option to record at a studio
처음에는 발표자분들한테 스튜디오 녹화도 선택지에 있었어요
You could record at a studio or using Zoom
스튜디오에 와서 녹화를 한다는 선택지 줌을 이용해서 녹화하는 방법
or record your presentation on your own
개별적으로 녹화하는 방법 이렇게 세 가지 선택지가 있었는데
We were going to start recording mid-August
원래는 이걸 8월 중순에 녹화하려고 했는데
but things got very serious then
8월 중순에 상황이 굉장히 심각해지면서
and we canceled recording at a studio
스튜디오 녹화를 전면 취소하고
and many presenters used Zoom to record their presentations
줌 녹화로 많은 분들이 대체하게 되었는데
At this time, two members from the Organizing Team and one presenter
이때 파이콘 한국 준비위원회 두 명 그리고 발표자 분 한 명이
met on Zoom and recorded the presentation
줌에서 만나서 영상 녹화를 진행했어요
Of course, we had created and distributed a video recording guideline for presenters
물론 사전에 발표자 촬영 가이드를 만들어서 공유하기는 했습니다
and I think we might reveal the guideline later on
촬영 가이드는 아마 추후에 공개할 수도 있을 것 같아요
While we went through 40 presentation videos
그리고 40여 개의 발표 영상들을 검수하면서
we checked to make sure that every video observed the CoC
CoC를 잘 준수했는지 이것도 일일히 확인했습니다
After all the videos were recorded, we edited them to be streamed
이렇게 모든 영상이 녹화된 이후에 외부 송출을 위한 편집 과정
and then captioned
모든 편집이 완료된 후에 자막을 제작하는 과정
After the captioning was done
모든 자막이 완료된 후에
we checked to see if there were any errors in the technical terms
기술적인 용어에 오류가 없는지 검수하는 과정도 거쳤죠
After going through this process, the presentation videos for
이런 과정을 거쳐서 참가자 여러분께서 이틀 동안 보신
the PyCon Korea 2020 that you've seen for the past two days were ready
파이콘 한국 2020 발표 영상들이 준비되었습니다
We thank all the presenters who have made time to share
바쁘신 와중에도 이런 소중한 경험을 공유해주시고
their valuable experiences to contribute to the Python ecosystem
파이썬 생태계를 위해 기여해주신 멋진 발표자 여러분, 정말 감사드립니다
Next is track management
다음은 트랙 운영인데요
The PyCon usually consists of five tracks
파이콘에서는 보통 트랙이 다섯 개로 구성된 경우가 많았어요
For example, we had split the COEX Grand Ballroom
예를 들면 지금 코엑스 그랜드볼룸이 101호~105호까지 나눠서 진행했었는데
However, during the virtual PyCon, we had to stream 40 session videos
온라인 파이콘에서는 총 40여 개 정도 되는 세션 영상들을
via YouTube Live over the course of two days
이틀 동안 유튜브 라이브로 공개해야 하기 때문에
so we split them into tracks like we always used to
기존과 동일하게 트랙을 나눠봤습니다
If you look at the track names
트랙 이름을 보시면
although, honestly, I'm not sure how this will change later on
사실 지금은 이런데 나중엔 어떻게 될지 모르겠네요
but the names are 101, 102, 103, 104, and 105
이름을 보시면 101, 102, 103, 104, 105 이런데
We named them in remembrance of COEX
이게 코엑스를 그리워하면서 붙인 이름이기도 합니다
Someone posted this on Twitter, and I asked for permission to show it here
이건 트위터에서 어떤 분이 작성해주신 트윗인데 허락을 받고 퍼왔습니다
"I heard that PyCon Korea will be held virtually"
"파이콘 한국을 온라인으로 한다고 하는데"
"Are they going to overlap the tracks and session times like they do offline?"
"혹시 발표 시간표를 오프라인에서 하듯 트랙을 겹쳐서 하진 않겠지?" 했는데
That actually happened
그 일이 실제로 일어났습니다
I hope everyone enjoyed the experience
부디 참가자 분들이 재밌게 즐겨주셨기를 바랍니다
Next is that the Pythonistas' meeting point
다음으로는 파이써니스타들의 만남의 장소가
changed from the COEX Grand Ballroom to Slack
코엑스 그랜드볼룸에서 슬랙으로 변경되었습니다
We made the decision to offer Slack
이때 미리 티켓을 구매하시거나 개인 후원하신 분들 대상으로
to those who bought tickets in advance or to individual sponsors
슬랙을 운영하기로 결정했는데요
We grouped the Slack channels by categories from the PyCon sessions
이때 슬랙 채널은 파이콘 세션의 카테고리 기반으로 묶어서 운영하고
so that the participants could have discussions more easily
참여하시는 분들이 조금 더 원활하게 이야기를 나누실 수 있도록 준비해봤어요
For those of you watching this video and will be preparing for another event
만약에 이 영상을 보시는 다른 행사를 준비하는 커뮤니티 분들이 계신다면
if you are registered as a non-profit organization
혹시 비영리 단체로 등록되어 있으시면
you can use Slack at a discounted price
슬랙을 이용할 때 할인을 받으실 수 있거든요
We used Slack during the event at a discounted price for
저희는 행사 기간 동안 슬랙을 운영할 때 비영리단체 할인 적용을 받았습니다
Next is a very important value of PyCon Korea
다음으로는 파이콘 한국의 아주 중요한 가치인
which is the CoC, the Code of Conduct
CoC, Code of Conduct 행동 강령입니다
Of course the existing CoC did contain content regarding
물론 기존의 CoC에도 온라인에서의 상황에 대한 내용들이
situations happening online
담겨 있기는 했어요
However, it didn't apply for an event that was only held virtually
근데 온라인에서만 열리는 행사에 대한 내용은 없었죠
so we supplemented this part
그래서 이런 내용을 보완했고요
For more details about the CoC
이런 CoC에 관한 자세한 이야기는 어제 진행된
there was a special session yesterday by the Python Korea Organizing Team
파이콘 한국 준비위원회의 또 다른 특별 세션
called 'Expanding the world one more step'
'세상을 한 발자국 더 넓히고 싶었던 우리의 이야기'에서
so please check out that video for more information
들으실 수 있으니까 그 영상도 많은 관심 부탁드립니다
Next is the merchandise
다음으로는 굿즈입니다
Actually, we were sad to let this part go due to the event becoming virtual
사실 이 부분도 온라인으로 변경되면서 아쉬웠던 부분 중 하나인데요
At PyCon, there is an event called 'Bag Insert'
파이콘에는 백인서트라고 해서
for the presenters, members of the PyCon Korea Organizing Team, or anyone
파이콘 한국 준비위원회 참가자, 발표자 누구든 상관 없이
Everyone would gather before the event where there are 1,800 or so eco bags
행사 전에 모여서 준비해둔 굿즈를 1,800여 개, 참가자 수만큼이죠
to fill with merchandised goods
1,800여 개의 에코백에 막 담는 이벤트도 있었어요
However, since that wasn't possible this time
근데 이번에는 이게 불가능했기 때문에
we had no choice but to use a delivery service
모든 것을 택배 기반으로 진행할 수밖에 없었습니다
We used Tumblbug
저희는 텀블벅을 활용했고
to sell T-shirts, which can't be left out at a developer event
텀블벅을 통해서 개발자 행사에 빠질 수 없는 티셔츠를 판매하기도 했고
and also to receive donation from individuals
개인 후원을 받기도 했습니다
Instead, we prepared merchandised goods so that you could receive them
대신 굿즈는 파이콘이 진행되는 9월 26일 전에
before September 26, the date of the PyCon
받아보실 수 있도록 준비하기로 했고요
The T-shirt manufacturer did the individual delivery
저희가 진행한 티셔츠 업체에서 개별 배송을 해주셨고
and even combined shipping for gifts and merchandise
개인 후원자 분들을 대상으로 보내드리는 선물, 굿즈까지 합배송을 해주셔서
so it was very nice
너무 좋았습니다
I'd like to take this time to express our greatest gratitude to our sponsors
이 자리를 빌어서 또 다른 방식으로 파이콘에 기여해주신 후원자님들께
who contributed to the PyCon in different ways
정말 감사하다는 말씀을 전하고 싶습니다
Next are the sponsoring companies
다음은 후원사입니다
Because PyCon became a virtual event
파이콘이 온라인으로 변경되면서
we had to change the benefits provided to the sponsors
후원해주시는 기업에 드렸던 혜택을 온라인 버전으로 개정해야 했어요
Also, the sponsors' booths that used to be set up in front of the Grand Ballroom
그리고 그랜드볼룸 앞을 가득 채웠던 부스
were changed to virtual booths
후원사의 부스 역시 온라인에서 버추얼 부스로 변경하게 되었습니다
For those of you watching this video, we'd greatly appreciate it
이 영상을 보시는 분들은 파이콘 홈페이지에 가셔서
if you visit our sponsors' virtual booths at the PyCon website
후원사 버추얼 부스 많이 방문해주시면 좋겠습니다
Despite the event becoming virtual
온라인으로 변경되었음에도 불구하고
we thank our sponsors for greatly contributing to running PyCon
파이콘 운영에 큰 기여해주신 후원사 여러분 정말 감사드립니다
This was our first-ever virtual PyCon Korea
저희가 처음 열리는 온라인 파이콘 한국이었기 때문에
so in order to focus on running this event smoothly
이 행사 좀 더 원활하게 운영하는 데에 초점을 맞추기 위해서
we had to cancel our other programs inevitably such as tutorials, sprints,
튜토리얼, 스프린트, 아이돌봄, 영코더와 같은  서브 프로그램들은
childcare service, and young coders
부득이하게 취소하게 됐어요
We hope that we will someday have the expertise
언젠가는 이러한 프로그램들도
to run these programs virtually as well
온라인에서 잘 운영할 수 있는 노하우가 생기기를 바라고 있습니다
However, we just couldn't give up the lightning talks
하지만 라이트닝 토크는 포기할 수 없었습니다
We used to receive presentation materials online on a first-come-first-served basis
기존에는 온라인에서 발표 자료를 선착순으로 받고
and then have the presentation at the site of the event
오프라인 현장에서 발표를 진행했는데요
This year, we received recorded videos on a first-come-first-served basis
올해는 온라인에서 사전 녹화 하신 영상을
Also, we made a hashtag event on social media
그리고 온라인 SNS 해시태그 이벤트가 새로 생겼습니다
In the past, we merely shared that we had a hashtag for our event
예전에는 그냥 해시태그가 있다는 정도로만 공유드렸는데
This year, we utilized hashtags to hold small events
올해는 해시태그를 활용해서 소소한 이벤트도 해봤고요
Actually, I'm talking in past tense but for me right now, this is a future event
사실 제가 지금 과거 시제로 말하는데 지금의 저한테는 이게 미래입니다
because as I mentioned before, this video is being recorded in advance
왜냐면 아까 말씀드렸다시피 지금 사전 녹화거든요
The main reason to have a hashtag event was because of our group picture
해시태그 이벤트를 진행하려고 한 가장 큰 이유는 단체 사진 때문인데요
If we had held PyCon at an offline site
오프라인에서 함께 파이콘에 참여했다면
we probably would have taken a photo holding a banner at the end of the event
아마 모든 행사가 종료된 이후에 현수막 들고 다함께 촬영했겠죠?
However, since that's not possible this year
하지만 이번에는 그게 불가능해서
we're trying to collect your photos for a group photo
여러분의 인증샷을 모아서 단체 사진을 만들려고 해요
If you are watching this video on September 26 and 27
9월 26일과 27일에 이 영상을 보고 계신 여러분
you will participate in the hashtag event, won't you?
해시태그 이벤트 많이 참여해주셨겠죠?
I will wish from the past that in the future, I would have put together
부디 미래의 저와 참가자 여러분이 함께 멋진 단체 사진을 만들어냈기를
a wonderful group photo with all of you
과거의 제가 바라고 있겠습니다
So I've shared what kind of struggles and steps we went through
네, 지금까지 저희가 어떤 고민을 했고 어떤 과정을 거쳐서
to hold our first virtual PyCon Korea
첫 온라인 파이콘 한국을 준비했는지 공유했습니다
Honestly, I thought preparing for a virtual event would be easier
사실 저희는 온라인으로 바뀌어서 준비하는 게 더 쉬우리라고 예상했어요
However, it wasn't easy at all
하지만 정말 쉽지 않았습니다
I know we weren't perfect in some areas but what I hope is that
부족한 부분도 있었겠지만 바라는 것은
you remember that PyCon Korea took place in 2020
2020년에도 파이콘 한국이 그 자리에 있었고
and how much fun it was for you
정말 즐거웠던 추억으로 여러분에게 남기를 진심으로 바랍니다
Lastly
마지막으로
From February until September 25 of 2020, our PyCon Korea Organizing Team
저희 파이콘 한국 준비위원회가 2020년 2월부터 9월 25일까지
prepared for PyCon Korea 2020
파이콘 한국 2020을 개최하기 위한 모든 준비 과정은
entirely online
모두 온라인 기반으로 진행되었습니다
Slack, Slack, Slack, Dooray!, Dooray!, Dooray!, Zoom, Zoom, Zoom
슬랙, 슬랙, 슬랙 두레이, 두레이, 두레이, 줌, 줌, 줌
Since we could only meet virtually, we really, really wanted to meet each other
온라인에서만 만날 수밖에 없어서 서로서로 정말 만나고 싶었어요
And to really wrap things up
그래서 정말 마지막으로
for the final two months before the event and even way before that
행사 막바지 두 달 동안 그 전에도 그랬지만
we spent more time together via Slack, Zoom, and Dooray!
슬랙과 줌과 두레이 너머에서 누구보다 심지어 가족보다 더 오래 함께 있었던
When one team finished its dawn shift, the morning team came
새벽반이 자러 가면 아침반이 등장하고
and then the evening team would take over after work
퇴근한 저녁반이 또 일을 이어나갔던
It was really tough, but we always tried to support each other
정말 많이 힘들었지만 언제나 서로에게 힘이 되어주려고 노력했던
To our beloved members of the 2020 PyCon Korea Organizing Team
제가 정말 사랑하는 2020 파이콘 한국 준비위원회에게
I'd like to say thank you to all of you as I finish this session
너무 고마웠다는 말을 전하면서 이 세션을 마치도록 하겠습니다
Thank you
감사합니다